A Guide to the Winn Family Papers, 1781-1894
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Winn Family Papers, 1781-1894
The Library of Virginia
21733
13 leaves and 89 pages
Winn Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Louis H. Stoneman of Columbia, Virginia, 2 July 1940.
Biographical Information
The Winns were a prominent family in Fluvanna County, Virginia. John Winn (1789-1844) served as a captain in the Virginia militia, and represented Fluvanna in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1828 to 1830. Winn also was a member of the Harrison Committee of Fluvanna County which supported William Henry Harrison for president in 1840. John Winn's son, Philip James Winn (1820-1887) was a doctor who also served as a superintendent for his district for the Conservative Party of Virginia during Reconstruction.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1781-1894, of the Winn family of Fluvanna County, Virginia, consisting of mainly of correspondence to Captain John Winn (1789-1844) from family, friends, and constituents regarding personal matters, the 1829-1830 constitutional convention, temperance, the general assembly, and election of brigadier generals. Also includes an indenture for an apprenticeship; a receipt; a catalog for seeds; a clipping regarding an estate sale; subscription and membership lists for the Harrison Committee of Fluvanna County; an insurance contract; reports of Superintendent Philip James Winn (1820-1887) for the sixth district, Conservative Party of Fluvanna County; and insurance companies information.
Contents List
- Deed, 25 April 1781, Richard Napier and Leonard Thompson, churchwardens for the Parish of Fluvanna, Fluvanna County, Virginia, binding Lizza Gallding as an apprentice to learn the "art and mystery of a spinster" to Lewis Kidd of Fluvanna County.
- Receipt, 18 February 1817, .to John Winn (1789-1844) for payment of taxes, from Edward J. Magruder for Valetine Wood Southall (1793-1861), Collector of the 19th Collection District of Virginia.
- Letter, 18 January 1829, from Joseph Key, Powell's Tavern, Virginia, to John Winn, House of Delegates, Richmond, Virginia, thanking Winn for his help in a case.
- Letter, 29 January 1829, from Barrett G. Payne (d. 1853), Fluvanna County, Virginia, to John Winn, House of Delegates, Richmond, concerning the House of Delegates' efforts to pass a bill organizing the state constitutional convention, asking Winn to collect a claim and make some payments for him, and sending social news from Fluvanna County. There is also a list of items on the back of the letter.
- Letter, 5 February 1829, from Barrett G. Payne, Fluvanna County, to John Winn, House of Delegates, Richmond, concerning the House's convention bill in the State Senate, Payne's requests, the weather in Fluvanna County, and social news.
- Letter, 17 February 1829, from Jesse Holman, Buckingham County, Virginia, to Charles Yancey (1770-1857) and John T. Bocock, Buckingham County's delegates in the General Assembly, Richmond, supporting Colonel Gideon Strange's nomination as general of the 3rd Brigade, Virginia militia.
- Letter, 19 February 1829, from Charles Woodson of Powhatan County, Virginia, to John Winn, House of Delegates, Richmond, supporting Gideon Strange as general of the 3rd Brigade.
- Letter, 6 May 1829, from David Shepherd Garland (1769-1841), New Glasgow, Amherst County, Virginia to John Winn, Fluvanna County, providing Garland's views as a candidate for the state constitutional convention.
- Broadside, 15 May [1829?], "Catalogue of Garden Seeds Sold by Joseph Rennie, G Street North East Side of Thomas Rutherfoord's Garden, Richmond."
- Letter, 15 May 1829, from Robert Rives (1764-1845) of Nelson County, Virginia, to John Winn, Fluvanna County, concerning his candidacy for the state constitutional convention.
- Letter, 21 July 1829, from Charles Cocke (1784-1861) of Albemarle County, Virginia, to John Winn, Fluvanna County, concerning his possible candidacy for the state senate in the next election and the political view of him in Fluvanna County. At time the letter was written, Fluvanna County was part of Cocke's senatorial district. After the constitutional convention, redistricting removed Fluvanna from his district.
- Letter, 19 September 1829, from Charles Cocke, Albemarle County, to John Winn, Fluvanna County, regarding his candidacy for the state senate and possible opposition over his alleged position on the calling of a state constitutional convention.
- Letter, 28 January 1830, from Robert K. Dabney (d. 1877) of Powhatan County to John Winn, House of Delegates, Richmond, supporting Charles Woodson as general of the 11th Brigade, Virginia militia.
- Clipping, September [1830], concerning the sale of land owned by Elias Wills, deceased, of Fluvanna County at auction by John Winn, trustee.
- Additional terms of sale, 6 October 1830, of the estate of Elias Wills by John Winn, trustee.
- Letter, 29 May 1832, from John Hartwell Cocke (1780-1866), Fluvanna County, to John Winn, Fluvanna County, asking him to join the Temperence Society.
- Letter, 25 August 1832, from Walker Timberlake, Fluvanna County, to John Winn, Fluvanna County, concerning possible flooding of his land as a result of work by the Rivanna Navigation Company.
- Letter, 7 December 1836, from George W. Thompson, Harrodsburg, Kentucky, to the postmaster at Palmyra, Fluvanna County, asking for news of family and friends in Fluvanna County and providing news from Harrodsburg. Thompson adds the results for William Henry Harrison (1773-1841) in Kentucky, Indiana, and Ohio during the recent presidential election. He states that land in Kentucky is selling well.
- Subscription list, [1840?], of contributors to the [William Henry] Harrison Committee of Fluvanna County.
- List, [1840?], of the Harrison Committee of Fluvanna County[?].
- List, [1840?], of certain subscribers to the Harrison Committee of Fluvanna County[?].
- List, [1840?], of certain subscribers to the Harrison Committee of Fluvanna County[?].
- Information, [1840 or 1844?], on the subcommittee of vigilance of the Fluvanna Clay Club.
- List, 1840, of moneys subscribed by the Harrison Committee and Tippecanoe Club of Fluvanna.
- Accounts, 1840, of John Winn, treasurer of the Harrison Committee and Tippecanoe Club of Fluvanna.
- Subscription list, 9 January 1840, to the Yeoman.
- Letter, 24 October 1840, from J. T. Winn, Richmond, to his father John Winn, Fluvanna County concerning some pamphlets and a dinner in Richmond for Leslie Combs (1793-1881) of Kentucky.
- Contract bond, 1868, between Edward M. Cleveland, Fluvanna County, and the Arlington Mutual Life Insurance Company of Virginia.
- Report, 15 March 1868, of the superintendant, Philip James Winn (1820-1887), of the Sixth District of the Conservative Party of Fluvanna County.
- Report, 17 March 1868, of the superintendant, Philip James Winn (1820-1887), of the Sixth District of the Conservative Party of Fluvanna County.
- "Charter, By-laws, Rules and Regulations of the Masonic Mutual Relief Association of Virginia," 2 March 1874, published by Bell, Browne and Company, Printers, Lynchburg, Virginia.
- "By-laws of Stonewall Lodge, No. 200, A. F. and A. M., Arvonia, Buckingham Co., Va.," revised and adopted September 1893, published by Baughman Stationary Company, Richmond, in 1894.
- "Manhattan Co-operative Relief Association," no date, of New York, New York.
- "Equality Life Insurance Company," no date, Richmond.
- Account, no date, of John Winn of certain money received and paid. On reverse side: "A system of regulations for the government of the 4th Brigade commanded by Brigadier General John H. Cocke."